Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is זבחים טו, Zevachim
Tet-Vav, זבחים Zevachim 15, we pick up at the bottom of יד
עמוד ב, Yud-Dalet Amud Bet, two lines from the bottom. אתמר, Itmar,
אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, we are in the middle of discussing the
act of הולכה, Holacha, first in the משנה Mishna the focus was
whether שלא לשמה, she-lo lishma, you know, invalidates by all of the
ארבע עבודות, arba avodot, and including הולכה, Holacha, the conveying of it
once it was received in a vessel the conveying it with the
vessel to the מזבח Mizbeach before it's thrown for זריקה Zerika on
the מזבח. Mizbeach.
And the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that even though it
is an עבודה, avoda, since it is an עבודה avoda that in
theory you do not need to do because you could slaughter the
animal right by the מזבח, Mizbeach, then it does not have the
power to change the status when you have a שלא לשמה she-lo
lishma thought during the הולכה. Holacha. So that's the position of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Within the discussion of הולכה, Holacha, we are now
discussing, put שלא לשמה she-lo lishma aside for a minute, we are
discussing the issue about הולכה שלא ברגל, Holacha she-lo baragel, that if
you conveyed it, if it was in place A and the מזבח
Mizbeach is place B, and there's 10 feet between them and now
the obligation of הולכה Holacha is even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
agree once it was slaughtered in place A, you have to do
the עבודה avoda of הולכה Holacha to get it from A to
B. Can you do that through, so the normal way would be
to walk it over, can you do it by passing it over?
Is הולכה שלא ברגל, Holacha she-lo baragel, does that count as the
act of הולכה Holacha or not? And that was the question was
raised yesterday. So we pick up with that two lines from the
bottom יד עמוד ב, Yud-Dalet Amud Bet, אתמר Itmar was taught, אמר
עולא, אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan הולכה שלא ברגל
לא שמה הולכה. Holacha she-lo baragel lo shema Holacha. No, it does
not count passing it, handing it over, you have to actually walk
it from place A to place B. Okay. Top of טו עמוד
א. Tet-Vav Amud Aleph. אפשר לתקונה או לא אפשר לתקונה? Efshar l'tikuna
o lo efshar l'tikuna?
Let's say according to this position of אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, that it has to be walked, it didn't work to pass
it, you know, to pass it. But now can you fix it?
So you passed it from place A and you handed it over
to somebody who was standing at place X, some midpoint between A
and B. That did not count as an act of הולכה. Holacha.
So was that like nothing? It wasn't good, it wasn't bad, it
just was nothing, and therefore bring it back to place A and
now walk it over from A to B. That would be אפשר
לתקונה, efshar l'tikuna, it could be fixed. Or do we say no,
it's לא אפשר לתקונה, lo efshar l'tikuna, that if you actually the
fact that it was moved and moved not through being conveyed by
walking is actually invalid, not just it's zero, but it's invalid and
it actually ruins the הולכה Holacha and now there's no way to
fix it. That's the question. רש"י Rashi also says it's relevant to
the question if a זר zar was involved, but we'll just focus
on this. תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear, the משנה Mishna
from later in the מסכת Masechet that we quoted yesterday. קיבל הכשר
ונתן לפסול יחזיר לכשר. Kibel hachasher v'natan l'pasul, yachazir l'chasher. A כשר
כהן kasher kohen catches the blood, you know, receives it in a
vessel, he's at point A, he hands it to a פסול, pasul,
one who's at point X, somewhere between point A and B. And
now the פסול pasul one כהן kohen just receives it, he's doing
a מעשה אצטבא, ma'aseh itztiba, like you know like a pedestal, he's
not doing anything, so it's not problematic that it's in the hand
of the פסול. pasul. And the simple sense of the משנה Mishna
is, okay, so now have the פסול pasul give it back to
the כשר, kasher, the פסול pasul who's at point X give it
back to the כשר kasher at point A, and now let the
כשר kasher at point A, you know, walk it over. Alright? So
that seems very clear that it's אפשר לתקונה, efshar l'tikuna, it can
be fixed. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואי נמי דיחזור
כשר ויקבלנה, V'hi nami d'yachazir kasher v'yikablena, the גמרא Gemara says remember
yesterday we suggested a different read of this ברייתא Braita and even
of this משנה, Mishna, an even more radical read, which is that
according to the side that הולכה שלא ברגל היא שמה הולכה, Holacha
she-lo baragel hi shema Holacha, that handing works, the reading was that
actually the כהן kohen now can go to place X, the כשר
כהן, kasher kohen, get it from the פסול כהן pasul kohen who's
standing at place X and continue now bringing it to B, that
the handing over was an act of הולכה. Holacha. Okay so that's
one way of reading it, that's not the way we're reading it
now because now we're saying we're reading it in the simple sense
that it has to be handed back to place A, because and
which is the simple sense of the משנה Mishna and consistent with
our position that הולכה שלא ברגל לא שמה הולכה. Holacha she-lo baragel
lo shema Holacha. So the גמרא Gemara says, let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. ואי נמי דיחזור כשר ויקבלנה, V'hi nami d'yachazir kasher
v'yikablena, it's like you know
obviously
it's a funny phrase, but it means obviously if you say that
you know the כהן kohen can go and pick it up from
the פסול כהן pasul kohen that he left it at, you know,
then clearly I mean everything is hunky-dory הולכה שלא ברגל Holacha she-lo
baragel is good, but even if that's not, okay, even if it
means that he has to go and receive it back at place
A, nevertheless you know אי סלקא דעתך לא אפשר לתקונה, eesalkatach lo
efshar l'tikuna, if so lo, but if
but okay read the משנה Mishna the simple way that you know
he has to go bring it back to place A, nevertheless you
know... If you said that you can't fix it, how is this
going to work? Either he picks it up at place X, which
means that even the הולכה שלא ברגל holacha shelo baregel was good,
or it gets handed back to place A, but that still means
that it's אפשר לתיקונא, efshar letikuna, it can be fixed. So that
seems to be very clearly the answer to our question. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. מי סברת דקאי זר גואי? Mi savrat dekai
zar gavai? No, דקאי זר בראי. dekai zar barai. Who tells you
that the X point where the non-כהן kohen is standing is more
interior, is closer to the altar? Maybe it's more exterior. Maybe it's
behind point A, not between A and B, but behind point A.
And if it's behind point A, then everybody agrees that that's zero.
You're not even moving it into the direction of the מזבח. mizbeach.
Okay, so now what we've said is like this. You have to...
the מצוה mitzvah of הולכה holacha or the עבודה avodah of הולכה
holacha is to convey it by foot, to walk it over. If
you handed it over, that doesn't count as הולכה. holacha. Does that
count as something that's bad and that invalidates, or does it count
as nothing? So the גמרא Gemara says well, if you hand it
in the wrong direction, it obviously is nothing. That's... and that could
be the case of our משנה. Mishnah. Then you know, hand it
back and pick up where you left off. That was zero. If
you hand it in the right direction and you're moving it towards
the מזבח, mizbeach, but you did it through handing it and not
through walking it, then our question is still open. Does that invalidate
or is it zero and therefore you can do a do-over?
Okay. איתמר, Itmar, it was thought, אמר עולא Amar Ulla, אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan הולכה שלא ברגל פסולה. holacha shelo baregel pesula.
Okay, so now what we just said, that... oh sorry, no this
is different. A different version of this is not הולכה שלא ברגל
לא שמה הולכה, holacha shelo baregel lo shemah holacha, it doesn't constitute
הולכה, holacha, but this is much more clear that it actually has
invalidating power.
Conveying it not by the foot is invalid. אלמא לא אפשר לתיקונא.
Alma lo efshar letikuna. So using the language not of it doesn't
count, but it's invalid, seems that it really invalidates the whole process.
So that means it can't be fixed. All right. So איתיביה רב
נחמן לעולא. Eitiveih Rav Nachman le'Ulla. So now we're going to challenge
this on things that seem like you know, it can be fixed.
נשפך מן הכלי על הרצפה, Nishpach min hakli al haritzpa, let's say,
you know, the כהן kohen caught it at point A, you know,
received it in the vessel, and then as he was moving it
from A to B and it spilled, you know, the blood he
tripped and he spilled and it's on the ground.
Okay.
ואספו כשר. Ve'asfo kasher. And okay, pick it up from the ground,
you know, put it back into your bowl and you can keep
on going. That's okay.
But now we've got a problem. So what's the problem? If you,
you know, you're at point X when you slip and you trip
and it... and it spills, so some of that blood is going
to spill towards between the space between point X, the midpoint, and
B, the מזבח. mizbeach. All right. So that is הולכה שלא ברגל.
holacha shelo baregel. Some of that blood has been moved towards the
מזבח. mizbeach. And now you're going to... so that should invalidate the
whole thing. You're going to put it back in the כלי, kli,
that's like walking it back, and now you're going to go and
bring it to the מזבח, mizbeach, but it already moved some of
the direction towards the מזבח שלא ברגל. mizbeach shelo baregel. All right.
It seems a little funny because you might think it has to
be something that's considered as like
human conveyance, you know, has the power of invalidating. But you know,
here too, your energy moved it, you know, you spilled it. Maybe
that's like it... you know, through your act it was pushed towards
the מזבח. mizbeach. It moved towards the מזבח mizbeach but not by
walking it. That should invalidate. הכא במאי עסקינן כשיצא לחוץ. Hacha bemai
askinan kesheyatza lachutz.
So no, what we're talking about is it didn't... the blood didn't
spill from point X to point B. It didn't spill in that
direction. It only spilled from point X back to point A in
the opposite direction. And therefore it didn't move towards the מזבח. mizbeach.
So the גמרא Gemara is a little incredulous. The גמרא Gemara says
לבראי נפיק לגואי לא עייל? Levarai nafik legavai lo ayeil?
What? It can work, it can move backwards, it can spill towards
towards you know, away from the מזבח, mizbeach, but somehow magically none
of it is going to spill towards the מזבח? mizbeach? Of course
if you... if you spill at point X, some of it is
going to go in the space between X and B.
So the גמרא Gemara says במקום מדרון. Bemakom midron. No, well what
we're talking is is that it was a slight incline on the
floor, which is pretty funny. You imagine that the floor was done,
you know, they leveled the place, it was totally flat. But it
was a slight incline and therefore yes, all the blood, you know,
between point X and point A, there's an upward... point B, there
was an upward incline, so all the blood spilled backwards between X
and between X and A. It did not move to... between X
and B. איבעית אימא בגומא, Iba'it eima beguma,
or right at point X there was a little indentation in the
floor and it all collected there and none of it moved beyond
point X. ואיבעית אימא בסמיכה, Ve'iba'it eima besmicha, or the blood is
very thick, you know, it coagulated, so it all just landed exactly
where it fell. So the גמרא Gemara says... ואכפיל תנא לאשמעינן כל
הני *Ve-achpil tana l'ashmeinan kol hanei*? What, the תנא *Tana* is going
out of his way, you know, just to be talking about these
special cases? Which means if the משנה mishna, *Mishna* says it's okay,
it's okay. Like, you know, you're gonna twist yourself into a pretzel
to say it's talking about these particular cases that you described. ועוד
*Ve-od*,
and in addition, so it clearly seems that even if it moves,
the פשט *pshat* is between X and B, it's still not going
to invalidate. ועוד *Ve-od*, and in addition, דתני באידך פירקא *da-tani be-idach
pirka*, since we taught in another פרק perek, *Perek*, later פרק perek
*Perek*, נשפך על הרצפה ואספו פסול pasul. *nispach al hartzpa ve-asfo pasul*,
that if it was
rather than was received in the כלי שרת *klei sharet* and then
spilled, but if it went straight from the neck of the animal
to the ground, it was not initially caught from the neck of
the animal into the כלי *kli*, it went straight to the ground,
so you never had an act of קבלה kabbala *kabbalah*, then it's
פסול pasul, *pasul*, it's invalid, okay? Because you need it to start
with קבלה kabbalah, *kabbalah*. The spilling is only okay if it happened
in the middle of the הולכה holacha *holacha*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says if that, why is it going to that extreme case
to say it's invalid? According to you, לפלוג בדידיה *liflog bedidei*, you
could take a distinction even in the case of הולכה holacha *holacha*.
במה דברים אמורים *Bamei devarim amurim*, when is a case when you
spill it during הולכה holacha *holacha* that you can pick it up
and it's kosher, mop it up or whatever? במה דברים אמורים בשיצא
לחוץ l'chutz, *Bamei devarim amurim be-she-yatza lachutz*, if it spilled away from
the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*. אבל נכנס לפנים *Aval nichnas l'ifnim*, if it
spilled towards the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*, פסול pasul *pasul*, then it's invalid.
So it should have said that if that was actually the case.
And it didn't. So clearly the sense here is that even if
it moves towards the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*, it's going to be kosher.
So you see תיובתא תיובתא *tyuvta tyuvta*, that is an absolute contradiction
to the idea that it can't be fixed. It might be true
that it doesn't count and you have to convey it by, you
know, through walking it. But even if it moved towards the מזבח
mizbeach. *mizbe'ach* in another way, and this would include the case of
handing it over, okay, handing it over, spilled or whatever, even if
it doesn't count, it doesn't, it's not פסול pasul. *pasul*. It doesn't
invalidate. It's just zero, and therefore you can move it back to
point A and do it again, okay,
or pick it up where it spilled, you know, and move it
back to the point where you tripped and it spilled it, and
then continue to move it forward. אתמר *Itmar*, now it was taught,
הולכה שלא ברגל holacha shelo baregel, מחלוקת רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon ורבנן
*Holacha she-lo beregel machloket Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabanan*. Okay, so the, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's not this,
it's a little confusing how to read this next section of the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, but we're going to go with how רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* reads it. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, according to this reading,
is going to do something very strange and is going to try
to redefine the whole debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
and the רבנן rabanan *Rabanan* in the משנה mishnah. *Mishna*. According to
the obviously simple פשט *pshat* of the משנה mishnah *Mishna*, the debate
is a normal הולכה ברגל holacha baregel. *holacha beregel*, a normal conveyance,
and that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says מחשבה machshavah שלא
לשמה shelo lishma *machshava she-lo lishma* does not invalidate because, in theory,
you could do it right by the side of the מזבח mizbeach,
*mizbe'ach*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is now going to say no,
no, no, that's not what they're debating at all. What they're really
debating is connected to this issue of הולכה holacha שלא ברגל shelo
baregel, *holacha she-lo beregel*. Okay, so how does that work out? So
it says like this, that הולכה holacha שלא ברגל baregel. מחלוקת רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon. ורבנן *holacha she-lo beregel machloket Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabanan*. So
that the debate of רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* and the
רבנן rabanan, *Rabanan* in the משנה mishnah, *Mishna* is not about normal
הולכה holacha *holacha*, normal הולכה holacha *holacha* when you're walking it, but
when רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says that הולכה holacha *holacha* is not
an עבודה avodah *avodah* and it doesn't invalidate, he's talking about a
הולכה holacha *holacha* that you do just by handing it over. Now
of course that doesn't fit in the משנה mishnah *Mishna* at all
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to challenge it. In the
משנה mishna, *Mishna* he emphasizes the reason because in theory it could
be done right by the side of the altar. But anyway this
is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is suggesting. That what they're really
debating is just the case of הולכה holacha, שלא ברגל *holacha she-lo
beregel*. Okay, and that's where רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says that it's
not an עבודה avoda. *avodah* and it doesn't count and your מחשבה
machshavah *machshava* doesn't work. And the רבנן rabanan? *Rabanan* say it is
an עבודה avoda, *avodah* and your מחשבה machshavah *machshava* does work. מחלוקת
רבי שמעון ורבנן *machloket Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabanan*. בהולכה רבתי דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דפסולה *Be-holacha rabati de-kulei alma lo pligi de-psula*. When it comes
to a big הולכה holacha, *holacha*, רש"י *Rashi* says what this means
is the normal הולכה holacha. *holacha* of walking it, everybody says that
that's an עבודה avoda. *avodah* and your intention can invalidate. כי פליגי
בהולכה זוטרתי *Ki pligi be-holacha zutraei*, when do they debate? In a
small הולכה holacha. *holacha*, a הולכה holacha שלא ברגל *holacha she-lo beregel*.
Now what does הולכה holacha. זוטרתי *holacha zutraei* mean? You know, so,
I mean, okay, it could be a special case when you did
a הולכה holacha, שלא ברגל *holacha she-lo beregel*, but what we're going
to see is that,
that what this means is even in a normal case where you
walked it over, now you're standing by the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach* and
you're throwing the blood on the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*. Well, there's a
degree of הולכה holacha, *holacha* that gets done there, from where you're
holding it against your body till you're moving your hands forward. That's
like a type of a הולכה holacha. שלא ברגל *holacha she-lo beregel*.
And maybe also, this is again where the גמרא *Gemara* gets a
little unclear,
maybe also, you know, as the blood is leaving your כלי *kli*
and it's on its way to hitting the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, that's
also conveying it שלא ברגל *she-lo beregel*. So it's at those moments
when רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says הולכה holacha. *holacha* isn't really an
עבודה avoda *avodah*, he means that. little הולכה holacha. *holacha* that you're
doing of like, you know, when you're standing by the מזבח *mizbeiach*
and you're moving the כלי *kli* and you're throwing it on the
מזבח *mizbeiach*. Now why we would call that הולכה holacha *holacha* and
not זריקה *zrika*, how that fits into the משנה *mishna*, none of
that really makes sense. So the גמרא *Gemara* is going to reject
this, but anyway this is how at least רש''י'ס *Rashi's* understanding what
the גמרא *Gemara* is saying at this point. Okay, so כי פליגי
בהולכה זו פליגי *ki pligi beholacha zu pligi*. So מחכו עלה במערבא
*machu ala b'ma'arava*, they laughed about this in ארץ ישראל Yisrael, *Eretz
Yisrael*. אלא חטאת העוף דפסולה במחשבה לרבי שמעון היכי משכחת לה *ella
chatas ha'of de-psula b'machshava l'Rabbi Shimon heichi mashkachat la*? The חטאת העוף
*chatas ha'of*, you know, the כהן kohen *kohen* uses his fingernail and
he cuts the back of the neck and the blood sprays out
from the חטאת *chatas* onto the מזבח *mizbeiach*, okay, and he does
it right by the side of the מזבח *mizbeiach*. So where is
the הולכה *holacha* for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*? Now of course you
might say where's the הולכה *holacha* for the רבנן Rabbanan, *Rabbanan* in
that case, okay, but so תוספות *Tosafot* says okay but you know
once the neck has been cut we would according to the רבנן
*Rabbanan* we would see that the blood that's in the still in
the bird that's now a dead bird, it's sort of like it's
in a vessel, okay, and the הולכה *holacha* is as you're moving
the bird you know closer to the מזבח *mizbeiach* that's and before
and you know the blood squirting out is the זריקה *zrika* but
the moving of the bird towards the מזבח *mizbeiach* that still would
be the הולכה *holacha*. But if for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* I
don't know why we have there has to be a הולכה *holacha*
here but anyway, but if for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, you know,
that is that does count as הולכה שלא ברגל *holacha shelo beregel*
and that מחשבה machshavah *machshava* isn't פסול pasul, *pasul* then where is
there in that type of a moving of your arm you know
with the bird towards the מזבח *mizbeiach* then where is there ever
a הולכה *holacha* that invalidates in the case of חטאת העוף *chatas
ha'of* for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*? דפסולה במחשבה לרבי שמעון היכי משכחת
לה *depsula b'machshava l'Rabbi Shimon heichi mashkachat la*? אי דחשב עלה מקמי
דליפוק דם לאו כלום הוא *ei de-chashav aleh mikamei de-lipuk dam lav
klum hu*. If you just thought about it before the blood came
out it's nothing. אי בתר דנפק דם איעביד ליה מצוותו *ei batar
de-nafak dam i'avid leh mitzvato*.
And if after the
blood came out then that's already the מצוה *mitzvah* of זריקה *zrika*.
Then there's so where exactly you know beforehand again it's I keep
on saying it's hard to get exact down this גמרא *Gemara* which
it is. But anyway but it sounds like what it's saying is
that you know the moving of the thing with the blood that
hasn't yet come out of it, that we could imagine as הולכה
*holacha*. But that is the moving of the
bird with the blood that is still in it. But that for
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that doesn't count as הולכה *holacha* and the
blood that's coming out that's already זריקה *zrika*. So where is that
moment of הולכה *holacha* that could invalidate for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*?
Okay, so גמרא *Gemara* says מאי קשיא *mai kashya*? Why is this
difficult? דילמא מדפריש ועד דמטי למזבח *dilma mide-parish ve-ad de-mati l'mizbeiach*. Maybe
from the time the blood came out of the neck and before
it hit the מזבח *mizbeiach* that's the moment where you could have
a מחשבה machshavah *machshava* that could invalidate. Alright. דהא בעי מיניה רבי
ירמיה מרבי זירא *deha ba'ei minei Rabbi
Yirmeyah me-Rabbi Zeira*. Rabbi Yirmeyah asked Rabbi Zeira היה מזה ונקטעה ידו
*haya maza ve-nikte'ah yado*. Let's say you know the כהן kohen *kohen*
was squirting from the the
so the כהן kohen, *kohen* was like either squirting the blood of
this חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of* or another case of יזה *yaza* means
that he was like רש''י *Rashi* says he was doing the sprinkling
of the blood you know with his of the inner חטאות *chataot*
okay with his finger you know like on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
okay you were doing so you were doing the sprinkling. But basically
the blood is flying through the air after the כהן kohen *kohen*
has done his act okay and here's the question. בעי מיניה רבי
ירמיה מרבי זירא היה מזה *ba'ei minei Rabbi
Yirmeyah me-Rabbi Zeira haya maza*. So the כהן kohen *kohen* was sprinkling
the blood or squirting the blood out from the from the neck
of the חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of* ונקטעה ידו של מזה עד שלא
הגיע דם לאוויר מזבח *ve-nikte'ah yado shel maza ad shelo higia dam
l'avir mizbeiach*. Okay, it's like a classic type of גמרא *Gemara* hypothetical
but it's a great way of of understanding what's happening here. As
the blood is mid-air something happens, you know, a knife comes out
of nowhere and cuts off the כהן'ס *kohen's* hand. Alright, so he
now becomes a בעל מום ba'al mum. *ba'al mum*. Does it invalidate
it now that the blood hits the מזבח *mizbeiach*? Okay, ואמר ליה
*ve-amar leh* and he said to him פסולה *psula*, it's invalid okay
that he the כהן kohen *kohen* is a בעל מום ba'al mum
*ba'al mum* when the עבודה avoda. *avodah* gets done. The end of
the עבודה avoda. *avodah* is not when it leaves the כהן'ס *kohen's*
hand. The end of the עבודה avoda. *avodah* is when it hits
the wall of the מזבח *mizbeiach* you know. So therefore מאי טעמא
והזה ונתן בעינן *mai ta'ama ve-hizah ve-natan
bein'an*. It says he shall sprinkle or he shall squirt and he
shall place it on the מזבח *mizbeiach*. So the fact that it
hits the מזבח *mizbeiach* the עבודה avoda. *avodah* is considered to take
place you know throughout the time until it actually reaches the מזבח
*mizbeiach*. This is always a fascinating question within הלכה halacha *halacha*. Like
for example, you
know some Are you חייב *chayav* because once it finished cooking, we
now retroactively look backwards and we say, so your putting it on
the stovetop was the act of cooking? Or no, does the is
it do we have to see that the that you're sort of
involved in the process the whole way until it gets cooked, and
it's only when it gets cooked are you considered to have done
the מלאכה melacha *melacha* and by then it's already not שבת Shabbos.
*shabbos*. And there's a lot of, you know, other cases. One case
for example that clearly we focus on the beginning is planting a
seed, because the seed doesn't take root for a few days, and
if you take it pull it out before it takes root, you
weren't מחלל mechalel. שבת Shabbos *mechallel shabbos*. But once it takes root
a few days afterwards, retroactively your putting of it in the ground
was the act of זריעה *zriah* on שבת Shabbos. *shabbos*. So here
the question is, is the עבודה avoda, *avoda* the throwing and maybe
it does have to eventually hit the מזבח *mizbeach*, or is the
whole עבודה avoda *avoda* until it hits? And the answer was, the
whole עבודה avoda. *avoda* is until it hits and if it becomes
a בעל מום ba'al mum *ba'al mum* in the middle, it's invalid.
Okay, so once that's true that that's the entire עבודה avoda *avoda*,
you can say also that ah, so מחשבה machshavah *machshava* when the
blood is midair could also invalidate. And that's where the מחשבה machshava
*machshava* can invalidate by a חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of*. Now, it still
would not be considered the הולכה *holacha* part of the act. Okay,
which רש"י *rashi* sort of concedes. The גמרא *gemara* was sort of
where are you going to get מחשבה machshava *machshava* to invalidate with
הולכה *holacha* by חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of*, but this is and the
sort of the answer is, well, okay, but whoever said it had
to exactly be by הולכה *holacha*, we can still get מחשבה machshava
*machshava* to invalidate by חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of*. So when the כהן
kohen *kohen* uses his fingernail to cut the back, that's שחיטה shechita
*shechita*, can invalidate there.
There is no קבלה kabbalah בכלי *kabbala bekli*. There is no if
the, you know, if the moving of the arm towards the מזבח
*mizbeach* is הולכה *holacha* and for רבי שמעון *rebbi shimon* that's a
הולכה שלא ברגל *holacha shelo beregel* that doesn't work, so you can't
that won't invalidate but there still is a moment where your מחשבה
machshava *machshava* can invalidate
when
the blood is squirting out, okay, and going midair, that is still
the process of הזיה *hazaya* and that's where your מחשבה machshava *machshava*
can invalidate.
All right. So now the גמרא *gemara* says like this.
Where were we? כי אתו רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
ורב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע *ki atu
rav pappa verav huna breih derav yehoshua verav pappa verav huna breih
derav yehoshua* came from ארץ ישראל *eretz
yisrael* excuse me, came מבי רב *mibei rav* from the house of
רב *rav*, אמרי היינו חוכא *amri hainu kucha*. This is why it
was mocked in ארץ ישראל *eretz yisrael*. ובהולכה רבתא לא פליגי *uveholacha
rabta lo pligi*, are you telling me that they don't debate when
it is talking about, you know, a normal conveyance ברגל *beregel*? So
לא פליגי? והא כי פליגי בהולכה רבתא פליגי *lo pligi? veha ki
pligi beholacha rabta pligi*. So, you know, if you act what are
you talking about? If you take a look in the משנה *mishna*
I mean it's very funny. Don't they argue? Of course they argue
about it. But basically if you take a look in the in
the משנה *mishna*, okay, you know, he says that the reason it's
not a problem is because it's אפשר לבטלה *efshar levatla*. And in
a way that's the exact inverse of the way you framed it.
The the the throwing of it, the moving of your arm towards
the מזבח *mizbeach*, that might be a הולכה זוטרתא *holacha zutra* like
a small הולכה *holacha*, it's only the act of moving your arm,
but actually רבי שמעון *rebbi shimon* would say that is a there
מחשבה *machshava* does matter, okay? And that's yes, and your מחשבה *machshava*
by the חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of* your moving the arm that does
matter. Why? Because it's אי אפשר לבטלה *i efshar levatla*. That is
a necessary part of the act. So רבי שמעון *rebbi shimon* actually
that thing that you're saying is trivial, that's exactly where רבי שמעון
*rebbi shimon* would actually that's where he would agree with the רבנן
*rabbanan* that it's an עבודה avoda. *avoda* and that it's פסול pasul,
*passul*. And it's in the הולכה רבתא *holacha rabta* it's the big
thing, the walking, that's where he says that it's כשר kasher, *kosher*
and as it's spelled out explicitly in the משנה *mishna* because you
could שחט shechted, *shacht* it by the מזבח *mizbeach*. It's clear that
he's talking about the normal big conveyance and he says that that's
not an עבודה *avoda* because it's אפשר לבטלה *efshar levatla*. So what
was this crazy way of rereading him that was making it all
part of this debate of הולכה שלא ברגל *holacha shelo beregel*? It
has nothing to do with your הולכה שלא ברגל *holacha shelo beregel*
issue. Okay, אלא בהולכה זוטרתא כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דפסלה *ela beholacha zutrata kuli alma lo pligi depasla*. Fine, you're
right. By and now actually the גרסא *girsa* is דפסלה *depasla*. Okay?
With this small הולכה *holacha*,
you know, of the moving of it towards the מזבח *mizbeach*, every
everybody agrees that that does invalidate it. Again, there's a question of
a גרסא *girsa* here. But okay, that that does invalidate. That's a
necessary act even though it's a small act. כי פליגי בהולכה רבתא
*ki pligi beholacha rabta*, they argue by the big one. Okay, so
again a very strange גמרא *gemara* trying to figure out what is
this little one, how is it part of this act of the
חטאת העוף *chatas ha'of*, what was the גמרא *gemara* thinking initially, how
all of a sudden did they wind up realizing they were wrong
and reversing it. Anyway, but that's trying to fit רבי שמעון *rebbi
shimon* and the rabbis into the debate of הולכה שלא ברגל *holacha
shelo beregel*. Okay,
now we're going to move on to another point. הוליכו זר zar,
והחזירו כהן kohen וחזר והוליכו *holicho zar vehachziro kohen vechazar veholicho*.
Okay, so now... Let's talk, we're now talking about הולכה שלא ברגל
now. Okay, now we're going to talk about a normal case of
conveyance. Okay, and if it's done by a זר, zar, remember we
quoted upcoming, whatever משנה, that if the הולכה is done by a
זר, zar it's invalid. Okay?
So, right, that was the thing we quoted at the top of
יד עמוד ב, yod daled amud beis, זר ואונן שיכור ובעל מום
בקבלה בהולכה ובזריקה פסול. zar ve-onen shikor u-ba'al mum be-kabala be-holacha u-ve-zrika
pasul. So the זר zar moves it towards the מזבח. Now it's
פסול. pasul, And presumably it means it can't be corrected. But that's
actually what we're going to now ask. Same way we asked this
by שלא ברגל, now we're asking this ברגל. Can it be corrected?
If the כהן kohen walks it back to point A and then
does it again, will that work or not? Okay.
So, let's take a look. הוליך זר והחזיר כהן וחזר
והוליך. holich zar vehichzir kohen vechazar veholich. פליגי
בה בני רבי חייא ורבי ינאי. pligi bah b'nei Reb Chiya ve-Reb
Yanai. דבני de-b'nei רבי חייא Reb Chiya and רבי ינאי Reb Yanai
debated it. חד אמר כשר, chad amar kasher, one says it's כשר,
kasher וחד אמר פסול, ve-chad amar pasul, it's פסול, pasul. which the
language of פסול pasul. indicates. It didn't say it was nothing, it
said it was פסול. pasul, But okay. מר סבר אפשר לתיקונא ומר
סבר לא אפשר לתיקונא. mar savar efshar letikuna umar savar lo efshar
letikuna. Just like we were talking before by the less weighty, הולכה
שלא ברגל, now the same debate actually exists even by הולכה ברגל.
Even if a זר zar did it, actually conveyed it by walking
it, fine, as long as it can reverse, you can do it
again. Everything else can't be reversed, right? שחיטה shechita by a זר
zar can't be reversed. Once it's שחט, shechted. it's שחט. shachted, קבלה
of the blood by a זר zar, can't be reversed. You can
catch different blood, but you can't catch the same blood. That can't
be reversed. Throwing it on the מזבח can't be reversed. That's פסול,
Passul, it's פסול, passul, end of story. This is the one thing
that can be reversed, right? It almost also points out a similar
idea that this evokes, it's the idea of carrying on שבת. It's
the one מלאכה melacha that is not transformative. All right, and carrying
on שבת has a status of like מלאכה גרועה. melacha geru'a. It's
still a מלאכה that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa for, but it
somehow doesn't have the same weight in certain ways or oomph than
certain other מלאכות. melachos. What that means exactly we'll worry about when
we learn שבת. But anyway, okay, so here, this is something that
can be reversed, so maybe even if it's done by a זר,
zar it can be reversed. So that's the debate. מר סבר אפשר
לתיקונא ומר סבר לא אפשר לתיקונא. mar savar efshar letikuna umar savar
lo efshar letikuna. הוליכו כהן והחזירו וחזר והוליכו זר. holicho kohen vehichziro
vechazar veholicho zar.
Now let's say you have the reverse. כהן kohen... brought it from
point A to point X, which is midpoint between A and B,
and then a זר zar picked it up from him, walked it
back to point A and then walked it back to point X.
So basically just did a redo but now didn't effectively change it
and he didn't bring it any closer to the מזבח. So the
גמרא says like this: אמר רב ששת בר אשי—actually, amar Rav Sheshes
bar Ashi אמר רב שימי בר אשי: amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi:
לדברי המכשיר פסול לדברי הפוסל מכשיר. ledivrei hamachshir pasul ledivrei hapasul machshir.
The debate would flip. The one who says that it's כשר kasher,
when a
כהן, kohen. when the זר zar brings it to point X and
the כהן kohen walks it back to A and walks it point
to X, so he's always looking, the way he's conceptualizing this, as
the person who did the last act,
the most proximate, that's how we define the process. So the same
way he says when the כהן kohen fixes it it's okay, so
if the זר zar redoes it, it's no good, because it's the
last act of bringing it from point A to point X that
is the one that we look at. So now it was done
by a זר zar and it's no good. And that's לדברי המכשיר
פסול, ledivrei hamachshir pasul, the one who's מכשיר machshir in the first
case focuses on the second conveyance, so here, which would focus on
the second one, it would be invalid. לדברי הפוסל מכשיר, ledivrei hapasul
machshir, the one who invalidates it when the זר zar brought it
to A and then brought it to X and then the כהן
kohen went back to A and went back to X, and he
says no, no, no, it's still
invalid, why? Because he says what happened afterwards is inconsequential, we always
just look at the first thing that was done. So according to
that, that he invalidates in the case when the זר zar was
the first person, here he would validate when the כהן kohen's was
the first person, because now that the זר zar brought it back
to A and brought to X, that's inconsequential, that's nothing. So he's
conceptualizing the debate of how do we look at guy number two.
Do we look at guy number two like that's the one now
that defines the process, or do we look at guy number two
as superfluous? And therefore the debate would reverse itself.
רבא Rava אמר—רבא says: אף לדברי הפוסל פסול. af ledivrei hapasul pasul.
No, even the guy, even the אמורא Amora who says that it's
פסול, when the זר zar, does it and then the כהן kohen
does it, that that doesn't make it now כשר, kasher. it's not
because we just look at the first guy. He would say in
this case where it starts with a כהן kohen, and then a
זר, zar he wouldn't say no, we just look at the first
guy and it's כשר. kosher He would agree it's פסול. מאי טעמא
דצריך לאמטויי? mai ta'ama de-tzarich le-amtuye?
Because in the end you have to bring it there. Meaning what?
Meaning in the case that the כהן... kohen. brought it to point
X. And then the זר zar brought it back to point A.
Once it was brought back to point A, now the blood is
in a place where it needs to be moved forward to get
to the מזבח. Okay, and therefore since it needs to be moved
forward to get to the מזבח, okay, that now has to get
done by a כהן. kohen. It doesn't work that a זר zar
is now doing it to B. Yes, if you step back and
look at the big picture, take out what the זר zar did
and the כהן kohen. we're back to where we started. But no,
when you break it down into the steps, once the זר zar.
brought it back to A, now there's an obligation of הולכה to
get it all the way from A to B and that can't
be done by a זר. zar Okay, so when the זר zar
started, the כהן kohen can't fix it because part of the way
the הולכה was defined was now done by a זר zar's and
that actively invalidates, okay, and when the כהן kohen starts, okay, the
זר zar doing it all ruins it because, you know, just because
the כהן kohen first stage made it כשר kosher, doesn't mean you
have a lock on it remaining כשר, kosher. okay? Now that it
was brought back to point A, now you still need to do
הולכה with a כהן Kohen and therefore if a זר zar does
it, it's going to be פסול. All right, very interesting. Top of
טו עמוד ב. Tes Vav Amud Beis. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרב
אשי, Amar lei Rabi Yirmeyah l'Rav Ashi, Rabbi Yirmeyah said to Rav
Ashi, הכי אמר רבי ירמי מדפתי, Hachi amar Rabi Yirmi miDifti, הצורך
להמטויי. ha'tzorech l'amtuyei. So exactly what you said, that's what, you know,
I'm sorry, this point that you said of הצורך להמטויי ha'tzorech l'amtuyei
that at the end of the day you have to still bring
it and now it's an עבודה that has to be done by
a כהן, Kohen, that's what you said that therefore according to everybody
it would be פסול, that actually is a מחלוקת רבי אליעזר ורבנן,
machlokes Rabi Eliezer v'Rabanan, is a debate of Rabbi Eliezer and the
Rabanan. דתנן, D'tnan, let's take a look. And now we're finally getting
to the last part of our משנה. We have Rabbi Shimon's position
that הולכה does not invalidate with מחשבה because in theory you could
do away with it. And we have Rabbi Eliezer's position in the
משנה that when you bring it in a direction you didn't have
to go, then that's not part of the process of הולכה and
it doesn't invalidate. So now we're going to say that's this issue
of are we now in a place that it has to get
moved? Let's see how he reads that in. דתנן, D'tnan, we taught
in our משנה, רבי אליעזר אומר המהלך ממקום שצריך להלך מחשבה פוסלת.
Rabi Eliezer omer ha'mahalach mi'makom she'tzarich l'halech machshavah pofeles.
If you do the הולכה in the direction you have to go,
you know, between point A and point B and you're going towards
the מזבח, that's where מחשבה invalidates. מקום שאין צריך להלך אין מחשבה
פוסלת. Makom she'ein tzarich l'halech ein machshavah pofeles.
If you go in a direction you don't have to go, you
know, you don't go a straight line between A and B or
maybe even go in the opposite direction, then your מחשבה does not
invalidate. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, and now Rava's going to clarify what
exactly this debate is in the משנה and then we're going to
see how it ties back to this issue of הצורך להמטויי. ha'tzorech
l'amtuyei. So Rava said, הכל מודים קיבלו בחוץ והכניסו בפנים זהו הילוכא
שצריך להלך. Hakol modim kibel b'chutz v'hichniso b'fnim zehu hilucha she'tzarich l'halech.
Everybody agrees that if you caught the blood on the outside, meaning
out away from the מזבח, you're always being מקבל בחוץ. mekabel b'chutz.
It doesn't mean out of the עזרה. azarah. Okay, you caught it
in place
point A and then you walked towards point B. Okay, that's a
הולכה you have to do and there מחשבה invalidates. קיבלו בפנים והוציאו
לחוץ. Kiblo b'fnim v'hotzio l'chutz.
However, if you caught it in point A and then you moved
it outward away from A, you know, out towards away from the
מזבח, not towards B, but, you know, in the opposite direction, okay,
זהו הילוך שאין צריך להלך. zehu hiloch she'ein tzarich l'halech.
Everybody would agree that that doesn't count as הולכה and מחשבה doesn't
invalidate. Okay, so when you go in the wrong direction, it's not
הולכה, everybody agrees. When you go in the right direction, it is
הולכה, everybody agrees. So what's the debate? לא נחלקו אלא שהכניסו וחזר
והוציאו. Lo necheleku ela she'hichniso v'chazar v'hotzio.
What happens is, is the way Rava's framing the debate, now, you
know, I would have said that there's a difference between בפנים b'fnim
and לחוץ, that the debate could have been not whether you moved
backwards from A or from A to B, but you didn't do
a straight line between A and B, you know, you took a
circuitous route. And there Rabbi Shimon would say, you know, your moving
away from the straight line is not necessary and it's at that
point that it's not a הולכה. But, you know, that's not what
Rava's saying. Rava's saying the debate is that you moved from A
towards B, שהכניסו וחזר והוציאו, she'hichniso v'chazar v'hotzio, and then you went
back towards A. And now you're doubling back and reversing yourself again.
מר סבר הצורך להמטויי. Mar savar ha'tzorech l'amtuyei. So the חכמים chachamim
say, look, you know, once you move back towards A, okay, going
back towards A was not a הולכה. Now you're back at A.
Now you're going to bring it from A to B. That's now
a הולכה again, you're bringing it in the direction you have to
bring it and מחשבה invalidates. ומר סבר הצורך להמטויי, V'mar savar ha'tzorech
l'amtuyei, now that you're back at A, now your new route is
a necessary route and that's all
הולכה.
ומר סבר לאו כהילוכא דצריך למהוי דמי. V'mar savar lav k'hilucha d'tzarich
l'mehvei dami. No, yes, right now you have to move. But the
whole thing was unnecessary. You could have stayed at point X, you
didn't have to reverse yourself and go back to A. So since
in the macro, this whole thing is unnecessary, when you're moving it
back from A to X, where you were in the first place,
that's no, that's not הולכה, that's just getting back to where you
were in the first place. Okay, so the way רבא Rava is
framing the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים, Chachamim,
you know, they're not talking about non-straight lines, they're talking about, which
is how I would have said it, they're talking about whether you're
doubling back or not. When you go in the opposite direction, not
הולכה, when you go in the right direction, yes הולכה. The debate
is, you went from A to X, which was towards B, and
then you doubled back towards A and now you're going again from
A to B. Okay, and now that you're going again from A
to B, the חכמים Chachamim say, well, right now that's the direction
you have to go. And רבי שמעון is saying, and רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, excuse me, is saying that no, big picture this is
duplicative and therefore it was unnecessary in the big picture and therefore
the going from A again to X where you were already does
not constitute הולכה. So that which you wanted to sort of say,
that question, now you're back, now it does constitute because now you're
back where you started, okay, and you don't get to look at
it big picture and say what the זר Zar, is doing is
was duplicative and unnecessary, that actually is the debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, that was what was said.
איתיביה אביי, eitivei Abaye, אביי Abaye challenged this read, רבי אליעזר אומר
המהלך מקום שצריך להלך מחשבה פוסלת. Rabbi Eliezer omer hamahalech makom she-tzarich
le-halech machshava poselet. Here we have a ברייתא braita that says if
you go in the way it has to, you know, that's necessary,
that's where מחשבה does invalidate. Okay, that was our משנה, but this
is a ברייתא braita and the ברייתא braita continues and says, gives
you, and describes it. כיצד? keitzad? קיבלה בחוץ והכניסה לפנים זהו הילוך
שצריך להלך. kiblah be-chutz ve-hichnisah lifnim zehu hiluch she-tzarich le-halech.
If you were on the outside and moved inside, you went from
A to B, that's a necessary הולכה. It invalidates. קיבלה בפנים והוציאה
לחוץ זהו הילוך שאין צריך להלך. kiblah bifnim ve-hotziah lachutz zehu hiluch
she-ein tzarich le-halech. If you, if you were, went, you know, caught
it at A and moved backwards away from A to the outside,
זהו הילוך שאין צריך להלך. zehu hiluch she-ein tzarich le-halech. Okay,
you know, if you moved it away from A outwards, that's not
necessary. Okay, that again presumably everybody would agree. But then the ברייתא
braita continues, and the word הא ha here is extra, the ברייתא
braita continues: חזר והכניסה. chazar ve-hichnisah. Now, you moved it, you know,
behind A and now you're bringing it back to A, back to
your starting point, זהו הילוך שצריך להלך הוא. zehu hiluch she-tzarich le-halech
hu. That is a הילוך שצריך להלך. hiluch she-tzarich le-halech. And even
רבי שמעון agrees that when you double back, since you got it
to, since you're now, the, now it's necessary, it continues to be
considered, you know, it continues to be necessary. So your framing, רבא's
Rava framing, that the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
חכמים Chachamim
is
a debate of whether you look micro or macro when something didn't
have to happen, but now it's, you know, big picture, but now
it's necessary, that's not true. In the ברייתא braita it says that,
you know, that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree that you look
micro, that if you walked behind, now getting back to where you
started is necessary. So it's not unnecessary.
So that framing of צריך לאמטוייה tzarich le-amtuyei is a debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן is not true. The ברייתא
braita makes it clear that even רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, who emphasizes
that there's a type of walking that is unnecessary, says, does not
call this the type of walking that's unnecessary. Okay, when you brought
it back, you know, when you, when you're now behind where you
were and you're now duplicating an effort, at this moment it is
still necessary and even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say it's necessary
and מחשבה invalidates. Okay, so you see that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is not taking this big picture and saying big picture it was
duplicative. He agrees that right now if it's necessary, it's necessary and
מחשבה's a problem. So everybody agrees to צריך לאמטוייה tzarich le-amtuyei is
a, is a thing. Once you're here, now it's necessary. So he
says, אמר ליה אי תניא תניא. amar lei ei tanya tanya. Look,
if it's a ברייתא, braita, it's a ברייתא, braita, I can't disagree.
Conceptually, I would like to understand that this is the debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן, but if the ברייתא braita
makes or רבא Rava would like to understand that, but if the
ברייתא braita makes it clear that for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer even
this is considered צריך לילך, tzarich leilech, then fine, then he considers
it צריך לילך. tzarich leilech. So then the question is what for
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is the place where it's אין צריך להלך?
ein tzarich le-halech? What is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying that's different
from the רבנן? So again, I would like to interpret it in
a way that it's not towards or away, but it's orthogonal, like,
you know, you move, you know, north or south, not east or
west, and then, you know, and that's unnecessary, but it's all in
the process of getting, you know, from east to west.
But that is not, the גמרא doesn't say that. And רש"י says
in the end really רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is not saying anything
different than the חכמים. Chachamim. He's just making it clear that he's
disagreeing with his father. His father,
רבי
שמעון, right, said that that in theory you could do away with
it then therefore הלכה
מחשבה is not a problem. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says I don't
care about in theory. Okay, the only thing I care about is
in practice. If it's something that actually is not necessary, fine, it's
not a problem right now. You went the wrong direction. But if
it's something that right now is necessary, then מחשבה will invalidate. I
don't talk about theoretically it wouldn't have been needed. So he's really
not saying anything different than the רבנן, he is just disagreeing with
רבי שמעון. It doesn't go by theoretically being unnecessary, it goes by
right now do you need to do it or not. Okay, הדרן
עלך כל הזבחים. Hadran alach kol hazvachim. That is the end of
כל הזבחים kol hazvachim with a whole discussion of שלא לשמה shelo
lishma that was really the focus, but it also got us in
here at the end since שלא לשמה is by all of the
four עבודות avodot to a focus on particularly the weight and the
definition of הולכה as an עבודה. Okay, now we start a new
פרק, perek which is all about a different topic and about who
is the status of people that invalidate the עבודה, not a thought,
but of people that invalidate the עבודה. כל הזבחים שקיבלו דמן. Kol
hazvachim shekiblu daman. You see the first פרק is called כל הזבחים.
kol hazvachim. The second one also opens with כל הזבחים, kol hazvachim,
so the name of the second פרק if you look at the
top of טז עמוד א tet zayin amud aleph is כל הזבחים
שקיבלו דמן. kol hazvachim shekiblu daman. Okay, you have to add the
next phrase. כל הזבחים שקיבלו דמן, Kol hazvachim shekiblu daman, any of
the זבחים zvachim that you caught the blood. We're starting with קבלה,
we're not starting with שחיטה shechita because שחיטה can be done by
a non-כהן. Kohen So we want to start by the קבלה because
we want to list all the invalidities including those that are specific
to being a כהן. Kohen. Okay,
כל הזבחים שקיבלו דמן, kol hazvachim shekiblu daman, that was that the
blood was caught, received in the vessel. זר, zar. if it was
done by a non-כהן. Okay, a ישראל, אונן onen or a כהן
that had somebody had just, you know, an immediate relative had died
that day. טבול יום, T'vul yom, he had gone to the מקווה
mikvah and, and, you know, he had some טומאה, tumah, he touched
a dead rodent or an animal or something, he went to the
מקווה mikvah and he's mostly טהור tahor but only when the sun
sets is he considered totally טהור. tahor. But after going to the
מקווה mikvah he's a שני sheini but he still invalidates if he
touches תרומה terumah or קדשים kodshim and only when the sun sets
is he totally טהור. tahor. Okay, so if he's a טבול יום
t'vul yom but also in terms of his personal status, even unrelated
to the טומאה טהרה tumah tahara issue, the fact that he's doing
the עבודה as a טבול יום t'vul yom invalidates the עבודה. מחוסר
כיפורים Mechussar kippurim or even if he's lesser than that. He was
a זב zav let's say, and, you know, went through the whole
process, he counted seven days, he went to the מקווה, mikvah, it's
nightfall, he's mostly טהור tahor now but he's now more like he's
in the status of even at nightfall of somebody who is lacking
his atonement or lacking the קרבנות korbanot that finish the טהרה tahara
process. And that's when he brings the קרבנות korbanot the next morning
and until that point he's sort of in the status of like
a שלישי. shelishi. Okay, and he can make קדשים kodshim invalid when
he touches it. So that's called מחוסר כיפורים. mechussar kippurim. That also
as a personal status invalidates the עבודה. ומחוסר בגדים, U'mechussar begadim, if
he's missing his, he's not wearing, you know, the בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna that we'll see makes him like a זר. zar? שלא רחוץ
ידים ורגלים, Shelo rachutz yadayim v'raglayim, he didn't do the washing of
the hands that a כהן has to do before the עבודה. ערל,
Arel, if he is uncircumcised even if he's a פרום frum Jew,
like רש״י Rashi says it's a family of hemophiliac, it was not
his fault but nevertheless that invalidates him. טמא, Tamei, if he's fully
טמא, tamei, I mean clearly it's true once we talked about even
people that went to the מקווה. mikvah. Okay, יושב, yoshev, if he's
sitting and not standing when he's doing it, or עומד על גבי
כלים, omed al gabei kelim, if he is standing but it's on
top of something, it doesn't have to mean a vessel, could be
on a rock, on a carpet, it could be he's wearing his
socks. Okay, his feet have to directly be touching the floor. אגבי
בהמה, Agabei behema, if he's standing on an animal. אגבי רגלי חבירו,
Agabei raglei chaveiro, standing even on the foot of his friend. פסול,
in all those cases it invalidates those sacrifices. קיבל בשמאל פסול, Kibbel
b'smol passul, רבי שמעון מכשיר, Rebbe Shimon machshir, but he catches in
the left hand it's פסול, but here רבי שמעון says it is
כשר. We mentioned that actually earlier, we will see that more. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. זה מנלן, Za minalan, how
do you know that a non-כהן
invalidates? Now in all the cases the גמרא is going to be
focusing on not is it a violation to do it, are you
prohibited against doing it, but how do you know that if you
did it it invalidates the קרבן. korban. דתני לוי, D'tani Levi, לוי
Levi taught, דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו לאמר וינזרו
מקדשי בני ישראל dabber el aharon v'el banav laymor v'yinazru mikodesh bnei
yisrael and they shall separate themselves, you know, from the sacrifices of
בני ישראל. bnei yisrael. So, you know, it says כל איש אשר
יקרב מכל זרעכם, kol ish asher yikrav mikol zarachem, the whole פסוק
pasuk is, let me read it inside. So here it is, it's
ויקרא כב, Vayikra chaf bet, it's the beginning of פרשת אמור Parshat
Emor or near the beginning, וידבר ה׳ אל משה לאמר, Vayidaber Hashem
el Moshe lemor, all this is about the כהנים. kohanim. דבר אל
אהרן ואל בניו וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל ולא יחללו את שם קדשי
אשר הם מקדישים לי אני ה׳. dabber el aharon v'el banav v'yinazru
mikodesh bnei yisrael v'lo yechalelu et shem kodshi asher hem makdishim li
ani Hashem. They shall separate themselves from the holy things of בני
ישראל, bnei yisrael, presumably it means when they are
טמא, tamei, not exactly clear right yet, just yet. Okay, and they
shall not desecrate my holy
name. Well, that's going to teach us that the sacrifice is invalidated.
And אמור אליהם לדרתיכם, Emor aleihem l'doroteichem, say to them for your
generations, כל איש אשר יקרב מכל זרעכם אל הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני
ישראל לה׳ וטומאתו עליו. kol ish asher yikrav mikol zar'achem el hakodashim
asher yakdishu b'nei Yisrael l'Hashem v'tumato alav. And now it says explicitly,
if you draw near to the sacrifices and your טומאה tumah is
on you, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מלפני אני ה׳, v'nichreta hanefesh hahi milifanai
Ani Hashem, then I am Hashem, you'll be cut off. Okay, so
that shows you that it's prohibited, טומאה, tumah, and that it is
מחלל. mechalel But what does that tell you about a זר? zar
Okay, so the גמרא says,
וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל. v'yinazru mikodeshei b'nei Yisrael. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
למיעוטי מאי? l'miutei mai? What does it mean saying that they shall
separate themselves from the sacrifices of בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael? And be
careful about טומאה. tumah. What's it coming to, what's the function of
the words בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael there? What's it coming to exclude?
למיעוטי מאי? L'miutei mai? אילימא למיעוטי נשים? Ilima l'miutei nashim? It's בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael and not בנות ישראל? Benot Yisrael? That when it's
a קרבן korban brought by women, they don't have to worry about
טומאה? tumah? So is that true? קרבן נשים בטומאה קרב? Korban nashim
b'tumah karev? All of a sudden because women bring it you can,
טומאה tumah is not a problem? אלא למיעוטי עובדי כוכבים? Ela l'miutei
ovdei kochavim? Okay, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and not non-Jews. So same
question. השתא ציץ לא מרצה? Hashta tzitz lo mirtzeh? The ציץ tzitz
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wore, you know, the gold plate
that said קדש לה׳, Kodesh l'Hashem, that it says that that atones
for עוון הקדשים, avon hakodashim,
you know, the sin of the sacrifices and טומאה tumah for the
sacrifices. And we actually say that that only atones for the טומאה
tumah of sacrifices brought by Jews. Okay,
because
it says, השתא דאמר מר, hashta d'amar mar, because we taught, עובדי
כוכבים בין בשוגג בין במזיד לא הורצה. ovdei kochavim bein b'shogeg bein
b'mezid lo hurtzah. That when there's a problem of טומאה tumah with
sacrifices of non-Jews, whether intentional or non-intentional,
the ציץ tzitz is not מרצה. mirtzeh. Okay, because it says לרצון
להם לפני ה׳. l'ratzon lahem lifnei Hashem. So even though non-Jews can
offer up sacrifices in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the ציץ tzitz
does not fix problems of טומאה. tumah. Okay, so once that's true,
that the ציץ tzitz doesn't even fix those problems, so if that's
true, טומאה קרב? tumah karev? So how could the תורה Torah be
saying טומאה tumah is a problem when it's Jewish sacrifices? What, when
it's non-Jewish sacrifices, טומאה tumah isn't a problem? טומאה Tumah is a
bigger problem. You don't even have the ציץ tzitz to help you
there. So that can't be what it means. אלא הכי קאמר. Ela
hachi ka'amar. This is what it means.
וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל ולא יחללו. V'yinazru mikodeshei b'nei Yisrael v'lo yechalelu.
That they shall separate themselves off from the קדשים kodashim that
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael וינזרו מקדשי, v'yinazru mikodshai, something like that.
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael have to distance themselves from my sacrifices. They
cannot be the one to offer the sacrifice lest they be מחלל
mechalel it. Okay, so they're reading בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, it's extra
the פסוק, pasuk, and it's coming to tell you they're part of
what has to be distanced from the offering of the sacrifice, the
non-כהנים, Kohanim, lest they desecrate, lest they invalidate. Okay, so that's one
דרשה drasha straight from the פסוק. pasuk. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, Debei
Rabbi Yishmael tana, at the school of Rabbi ישמעאל Yishmael we taught,
אתיא בקל וחומר מבעל מום. atya b'kal v'chomer miba'al mum. No, you
could learn it a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from a בעל מום.
ba'al mum Okay, because the earlier פסוק pasuk said in ויקרא כ״א
י״ז, Vayikra chaf-alef yud-zayin, דבר אל אהרן לאמר איש מזרעך לדרתם אשר
יהיה בו מום לא יקרב להקריב לחם אלהיו. Daber el Aharon lemor
ish mizar'acha l'dorotam asher yihiyeh vo mum lo yikrav l'hakriv lechem elohav.
Right? So
somebody with a מום mum shall not draw close. And then it
goes on to say, אך אל הפרכת לא
יבא ואל המזבח לא יגש כי מום בו ולא יחלל את מקדשי
כי אני ה׳ מקדשם. ach el haparochet lo yavo v'el hamizbe'ach lo
yigash ki mum bo v'lo yechalel et mikdashai ki Ani Hashem mikadesham.
Do not desecrate. Again, יחלל. yechalel. So בעל מום ba'al mum and
טומאה tumah are the two things that are explicit in the פסוקים
psukim that are מחלל the עבודה. Okay. מבעל מום. Miba'al mum. מה
בעל מום שאוכל. Mah ba'al mum she'ochel. Now a בעל מום ba'al
mum is allowed to eat קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. And nevertheless, that's
explicit in the פסוקים. psukim. אם עבד חילל, Im avad chillel, if
he does the עבודה, he makes the, he desecrates it. So top
of צ״א עמוד א׳. tzadi-alef amud alef. זר שאינו אוכל אינו דין
שאם עבד חילל? Zar she'eino ochel eino din she'im avad chillel? And
a non-כהן who's not allowed to eat the קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodashim?
So it's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that if he does the
עבודה he should invalidate it. That's a pretty good קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. A זר zar. is even more excluded from קרבנות. korbanot. So
certainly he should invalidate it. The גמרא says, מה לבעל מום שכן
עשה בו קרב כמקריב? Mah l'ba'al mum sheken asah bo karev k'makriv?
No, בעל מום ba'al mum has an extra weight. Not only does
בעל מום ba'al mum apply to the כהן, it applies to the
קרבנות. korbanot. So maybe because of that extra power of the בעל
מום ba'al mum in invalidity of it, that's why it invalidates the
עבודה. And it wouldn't be true by a זר. zar, Okay, so
how about טמא יוכיח? tamei yochiach? טמא Tamei is the other thing
explicit in the פסוקים psukim that it's ולא יחללו. v'lo yechalelu. That's,
you know, that doesn't apply to the קרבנות. korbanot. I mean, because
when there's still קרבנות korbanot before they're שחט, they're live animals and
live animals don't become טמא. tamei. So that doesn't have the idea
that applies both to the כהן and the קרבן. korban. It only
applies to the
כהן. מה לטמא שכן מטמא? Mah l'tamei sheken metamei? Okay, but טמא
tamei is weightier because טמא tamei the טומאה tumah spreads, it makes
other things טמא. tamei. And again, a זר, zar that doesn't affect,
you know, כהנים. Kohanim. His status doesn't spread. So the גמרא says,
בעל מום יוכיח. Ba'al mum yochiach. Okay, but בעל מום Baal Mum
will show you that that's not essential to invalidate, because בעל מום
Baal Mum doesn't spread and it still invalidates. וחזר הדין. V'chazar hadin.
And you go back and forth. Meaning, what makes בעל מום weightier
that it applies
to
the
קרבן... korban... What's true by this isn't true by that, הצד השוה
שבהן Hatzad Hashavah Shebahen the common
denominator שמוזהרין shemuzharin that both a בעל מום and a טמא tamei
are said they're not allowed to be מקריב makriv ואם עבדו חללו
ve'im avdu chilalu and if they did they desecrated it. So this
is going to be the general theme: somebody who's not allowed to,
if he does it desecrates it. And we learn that out from
the common denominator of בעל מום and טמא. tamei. אף אני אביא
זר, Af ani avi zar, I'll include a זר zar שהוא מוזהר
shehu muzhar that he also is prohibited to doing the עבודה ואם
עבד חילל ve'im avad chillel and if therefore it will invalidate. And
we'll pick up tomorrow to discuss how do we know that a
זר is prohibited to do the עבודה. We'll stop here.